Thomas Corwin Mendenhall Personal Papers, 1910-1999
Smith College Archives
- SERIES III. PERSONAL CORRESPONDENCE, 10 document boxes/ 4.2 linear ft.
  - [OVERSIZE MATERIALS (Box 16)]
    - Moulton, Sylvia [Fletcher] 1934-1949, 1962-1989, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Weaver, Toby & Marjory 1960-1997, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
- SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL RECORDS, 2 document boxes/ 0.8 linear ft.
  The Professional Records series consists of correspondence, reports, and organizations with whom Mendenhall was affiliated. The bulk of the information relates to professional work done at Yale, including reports on the committee on general education and specific proposals for the revamping of the history department. Also included is professional work done at Smith College [post-retirement] with respect to the Ada Comstock program and issues regarding coeducation. The last folder of material entitled 'Letters of Recommendation' is RESTRICTED.
  - College Entrance Examination Board 1955-1958 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Job Offers 1939-1948 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Prospect Hill School 1956 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Response to Broadcast on January 30, 1955 1955 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Smith College [Post-Retirement]
    - General 1972-1996 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Ada Comstock Program 1996 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Coeducation 1978-1987 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - War Department/West Point 1941-1944, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - World Caravan Guild, Inc. 1937-1938 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Yale
    - General 1932-1950 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - General 1955-1971 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - General undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Committee on General Education 1953-1957 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Committee on General Education undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Crew Team 1949-1950, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - S.B. Hemingway, Master of Berkeley College 1949-1950 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Hemingway Retirement 1938-1950, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - History Department 1944-1945, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - "The Mendenhall Proposals..." 1954 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - "Yale's Stake in the Residential Principle..." 1957 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous 1937-1951, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Letters of Recommendation (Box 18, Folder 10)
    RESTRICTED MATERIAL
- SERIES V. WRITINGS and SPEECHES, 5 document boxes/ 2.1 linear ft.
  The majority of the Writings and Speeches series consists of research material for Mendenhall's publication entitled The Shrewsbury Drapers and the Welsh Wool Trade in the XVI and XVII Centuries (1953), which he worked on both as a graduate student and as a professor at Yale. Also included are articles, which are mostly related to his own personal work with relation to history, education, or crew and also issues that members of the Yale community found challenging and Smith relations. The series further includes speeches and quotable quotes that mainly pertain to Smith and Yale affairs.
  - General 1937-1947, undated (Box 19)
  - General-Publishers 1947, 1963-1987 (Box 19)
  - Research Material
    - General 1935-1936 (Box 19)
    - 1949-1950 Sabbatical 1949-1950 (Box 19)
    - Cradock
      - Letters from Sarah B. Ball 1952, 1955, 1956 (Box 19)
      - Letters from Sarah B. Ball 1959, undated (Box 19)
      - Agents & Apprentices circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - Agent Ratcliffe circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - Agents circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - Home-Essex circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - Will circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - at Medford circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - at Medford circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - Burgess "The Short Parliament" circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - "The Long Parliament" circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
    - "Colony Records" vs. Amer. Antiq. Soc. -Schurtleff vs. Haven circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
    - "Hiatus" circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
    - "Hiatus" circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
    - Cradock
      - General circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - Biography-Essex Institute circa 1928-1959 (Box 19)
      - Biography-Massachusetts Historical Society circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Biography-Roberts circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Genealogy-Miscellaneous circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Skinners of London circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Massachusetts Bay Company-Charter circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - East India Company-Charter circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - American Ante Massachusetts Bay Colony circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Endecott circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Chronology-Dorchester-Massachusetts Bay Interregnum circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Cradock
      - Biography-Rose-Troup circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Biography-Skinners circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Irish Property circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Acts of the Privy Council circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Cradock & Cokayne-Ships & Shipping circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Quo Warranto of 1635 circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Suffolk Deeds-Index of Grantors circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Cradock-Home-Wales circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Colony Records-Massachusetts circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Cradock-Biography-(A-B) circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Alderman Cockayne's Project & the Cloth Trade circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Tomb of Sir William Cokayne & his Wife circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Calendar of State Papers
      - 1513-1616 circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - 1617-1621 circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - 1622-1624 circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - 1625-1629 circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - 1513-1641 circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - New England Company-Rose-Troup circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Cradock
      - London circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Miscellaneous circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Massachusetts Bay Colony
      - Rose-Troup circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Miscellaneous circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Cradock-Biography-New England Historical Society circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - London-Church Records circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Cradock circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Letter to Winthrop circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Biography-Medford Historical Society circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
      - Genealogy-Chart circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Church Catalogue circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Cradock's Plantation-Medford Historical Society circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Brereton's Account of Gosnold's Voyage circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Levett's Voyage circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Waymouth's Voyage circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - "Description of New England" -Captain John Smith circa 1928-1959 (Box 20)
    - Records of the Governor and Company of Massachusetts Bay Colony-Young circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Cradock-Bibliography circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Winthrop Papers-Miscellaneous circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Colony Records-Miscellaneous circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Cradock-Genealogy-Chart circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Arthurian Ballad-Caradoc circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Cradock-Not Matthew circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Skinners circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Cokayne, Sir William circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Ancestry circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - House circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Calendar of the State Papers (Box 21, Folder 12)
      - 1630-1634 circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - 1635-1641 circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - Puritans circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - Cradock, Damaris circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - London circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Map of London circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - London Stone circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Cradock (Box 21, Folder 20)
      - Government in New England circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 21)
      - Correspondence-Miscellaneous (A-Z) 1955-1956 (Box 21, Folder 22)
    - Drapers-Research Book (Box 21, Folder 23)
      - A-F circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 24)
      - G-P circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 25)
      - R-Z circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 26)
      - Shrewsbury Drapers circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 27)
      - Shrewsbury Drapers-Correspondence 1949-1953 (Box 21, Folder 28)
    - Nationalism & Sectionalism in 19th Century America circa1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 29)
    - Slavery in Politics circa 1928-1959 (Box 21, Folder 30)
  - Articles
    - The American Way in Higher Education-The Yale Review undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - The Apse up to Year 1000 A.D. undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Books and Bookstores-New York City Conference for the National Association of College Stores 1959 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Chance and Change in Smith College's First Century-Smith College 1976 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Clio Need not be Bemused-with W.H. Dunham, Fr.-American Association University Professor Bulletin 1946 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - General Education through Specialization-School and Society 1954 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - The Great Depression of 1929-Social Education 1958 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Have Oar, Will Travel: Short History of the Yale Crew Team of 1956-Berkeley College, Yale University 1957 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - History and the Social Sciences-N ew England Association of Social Studies Teachers-Radcliffe College 1958 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Historical Revisions-The New England Social Studies Bulletin 1952 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - History of Art and the General History Course-with Summer Mck. Crosby-College Art Journal 1948 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - How Much History for the College-Bound Student-Social Studies Topics 1954 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Integrative Aspects in Curricula-Main Currents in Modern Thought 1955 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - The Introductory College Course in Civilization-The American Historical Review 1944 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Lecturing English and American-Universities Quarterly 1950 (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - Making History Come Alive-with James Howard-The Council for Basic Education 1982 (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - Mendenhall President of Smith-Yale Historical Bulletin 1959 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - The Mendenhall Proposals: An Intrigue in Three Acts-Berkeley College, Yale University 1954 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - A Merioneth Wage Assessment for 1601-Berkeley College, Yale University undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Rowing Dangerously-Eastern Sprints 1991 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - The Sabin and Mendenhall Papers, by Dorothy Schullian-Journal of the History of Medicine 1960 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Shrewsbury in New England-Transactions of the Shropshire Archaeological Society 1953 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Review of "Studies of Elizabethan Foreign Trade"-American Historical Review 1960 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - This Changing Yale-Yale Alumni Magazine 1948 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Women, Hercules, and Athletes-The College Board Review 1979 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Speeches
    - Berkeley College
      - Farewell to Mendenhall Transcript circa 1959 (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - 25th Anniversary of the College Plan at Yale 1959 (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - Senior Dinner May 1966 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - "A Brief Report on the Effect of the Ford Grant on Smith College" undated (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Commencement
      - Berkeley College 1959 (Box 23, Folder 14)
      - Smith College-"Perspectives" May 1983 (Box 23, Folder 15)
      - Smith College 1989 (Box 23, Folder 16)
      - S.P.S. May 1957 (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - Memorial Service for Bunting, Henry 1954 (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Montclair Academy Jun 1951 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - "Physical Education at Smith, Past, Present, and Future undated (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - P.H.S. Jun 1958 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Quotable Quotes undated (Box 23, Folder 22)
    - Teacher Training, New Style undated (Box 23, Folder 23)
    - "To the Class of 1960" 1985 (Box 23, Folder 24)
    - "The Transition to Yale Life from Secondary School" undated (Box 23, Folder 25)
    - Yale Miscellaneous circa 1950-1959 (Box 23, Folder 26)
    - "Women's Education and the Education of Women" undated (Box 23, Folder 27)
- SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS and EPHEMERA, 1 document box/ 0.4 linear ft.
  The Photographs and Ephemera series includes Mendenhall portraits, family portraits, portraits of friends, and photos taken during leisurely travel as well as while attending collegiate institutions. Also included are many crew and sailing photos, including a sailing album and Van Fisher sailing photos. There are several unidentified and miscellaneous photos located at the end of the series.
  - Photos
    - TCM Portraits circa 1920-1930s, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - TCM Candids 1930-1989, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Family 1950-1952, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Friends 1930-1990, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Germany Trip 1934 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Oxford 1934-1935 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Le Rosey circa 1920-1927, undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - TCM at Yale 1931-1959, undated (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Smith [Post-Retirement] 1977-1991 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Crew and Sailing 1934, 1950-1959, 1975, 1995, undated (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Sailing Album 1928-1931 (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Van Fisher Sailing Photos undated (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified and Miscellaneous 1929-1959, undated (Box 24, Folder 13)